Okay, so in this video we'll be talking
about
nuclear fission and nuclear fusion. So
let's
start with nuclear fission.
And basically nuclear fission, I'll write
this
down. Nuclear fission is
the splitting of a heavy nucleus into two
smaller
nuclei. So, splitting of nucleus
into two smaller nuclei.
And this results in a huge release of
energy.
So for example, if you have uranium, the
atomic
number would be 235, or the mass number,
plus
a neutron. This is achieved when you fire
a
neutron at one of those elements.
So nuclear fission only occurs when you
first
start the reaction by firing a neutron at
whatever
your element is. And it results in other
fragments, so we call these fission
fragments,
plus a couple of more neutrons, plus let's
say
X neutrons, and plus energy.
And the reason why nuclear fission is so
slow,
it has such a big release of energy, is
that
there is obviously going to be more than
one
atom of whatever you're undergoing fission
to.
And each of these, after you fire the
first
neutron, it's going to release energy
of all, and it's going to release more
neutrons.
And these extra neutrons are going to hit
more
atoms of, in this case, uranium, and it's
going
to keep on going, so a chain reaction.
And that can be used to produce a lot of
dangerous
things, such as atomic bombs.
Yeah, atomic bombs rely on nuclear
fission,
and this is a good diagram illustrating
it.
Oops, don't know what happened there.
As you can see, you first fire a neutron
at
it, and it's going to split, release more
neutrons,
and you're going to keep on going until
all
of your reactants is used up.
And this releases a lot of energy.
So, what happens here?
Well, when you split this, products are
more
tightly bound, because heavy nuclei have
lower
binding energy. Because, like we talked
about,
greater distance, less nuclear force.
And since products are more tightly bound,
the
mass also decreases. And if the mass
decreases,
then it must go somewhere, and that mass
is
converted into energy. E equals mc
squared.
Conservation of mass, it can't be created
or
destroyed, so the decrease of mass here is
converted
into energy. And in the chain reaction,
there
are three processes. The first one is
sub-critical.
You don't really have to know this that
much,
it really depends on your course and your
teacher.
It's when the reaction dies.
The second one is critical. When there is
a
steady reaction. And the third one is
super critical. When there is an
exponential
increase. So, critical
is at the exact middle of the reaction.
Because it's not increasing exponentially,
but
it's also not decreasing. And super
critical,
it's basically for most of the reaction.
Because it's going to be chained to ours.
Next one, we have nuclear fusion.
Let's talk about that. It's when you
combine
light nuclei into heavy nuclei.
For example, in the sun, hydrogen fuses to
form
helium. You have four protons, or
hydrogen.
And these form helium and energy.
Well, why does fusion release energy?
Well, from the binding energy curve, light
nuclei
have low binding energy per nucleon.
So that means that the medium nucleons
over
here are more stable. And that means that
the
binding energy per product increases.
Same thing for fission as well.
So this one is more stable, so mass
decreases.
And since mass decreases, energy increases
because
of conservation of mass. And fusion
requires
a lot of energy.
You must have high temperatures, extremely
high
temperatures. And
you must have high pressure. And this is
because
protons repel each other.
So they must overcome that electrostatic
repulsion
in order to fuse.
And that's why you need high pressure. And
yeah,
basically overall, these are the three
main
things you have to know for atomic
reactions.
Decay happens in unstable nuclei.
They're heavy and they move towards
stability.
Fission, on the other hand, happens in
bombs
and reactors. The nuclei are typically
very,
very heavy. Otherwise, you won't be able
to
achieve fission. And they split into
medium
mass and release energy as well.
And fusion happens only in stars,
naturally.
And it's made up of light nuclei which
combine
to form medium nuclei.
And that's all for this unit.
So thank you guys for watching and we'll
see
you in the next one. Bye!